避免有人。
佢終於忍無可忍。
唔該，好多謝主席。
七號位嘅sam音。
決意沿住河邊跑上上游。
過咗一陣，同樣嘅情況又不斷重複喎。
好，噉我哋翻返嚟啦。咁咧，跟住就係九十。
要真正解決問題，就必須從源頭去出發。
揾出個中嘅原因，睇下係邊個去故意將人推入河入邊。
好似誒故事入邊嘅情節噉樣，推咗人哋去河入邊魚溺噉樣。
而家嘅情況就好似電子煙或者加煙噉樣，亦都必須從源頭嘅出發去改善呢個噉嘅問題。
所謂防患未然，我哋應該全面禁止另類嘅煙草產品，唔好畀呢啲嘅產品。
誒，我係希望全體嘅議員都係支持呢個誒條例嘅草案啦，同埋全面禁止另類煙草產品嘅。
但係喺佢救緊呢位遇溺者，亦都幫緊佢做緊心肺復甦法嘅時候，又有另一位嘅遇溺者從上游飄緊過嚟喎。
雖然啱啱救出嘅呢位遇溺者仍然不省人事，但係呢位路人本住良知，即刻跳入河邊將第二位嘅遇溺者救出嚟。
咁唔知道大家有冇聽過一個有關公共衞生嘅經典故事咧？其實從前有一位路人經過河邊嘅時候，佢就見到一個人雨溺喎，於是佢就跳入河入邊將佢救出嚟。
多謝。
好唔該，跟住係九十八號位嘅黎住黎主君。
嘅二手煙或者三手煙，影響自己同埋他人嘅健康。
十個司法管轄區並駕齊驅，共同建設唔受另類煙草產品困擾嘅社會。
最近其實可能大家都喺街上面都見到，好多年輕嘅上班族都開始吸食電子煙或者加熱煙。
唔以為咧電子煙咧，其實比傳統煙更加安全嘅，咁咧就好容易咧墮入咗啲陷阱啦。佢哋唔明白咧，可能電子煙係其實咧都會帶嚟引致一啲唔同嘅心血管問題啊，一啲呼吸系統嘅疾病啦，甚至乎係癌症等等危害嘅。
所以，除咗支持全面禁止另類煙草產品之外，我亦都希望所有嘅煙民都可以決心戒煙，鼓起勇氣，亦都希望各位嘅議員唔好因為部分嘅煙民可能轉食電子煙而犧牲咗其他廣大市民嘅健康。
禁止所另類煙草產品係冇理據，但係其實世界衞生組織一早已經指出，所有嘅形式嘅煙草使用都係對人體有害，當中包括今次條例草案中嘅三種產品，而且國際上亦都係有越嚟越多嘅學術研究去發現呢各種類型嘅煙草產品係點樣可以影響我哋健康。
係好似誒，因為好奇啦，又或者其他嘅原因，又或者朋輩嘅慫恿而吸食咗電子煙，最後食到上癮嘅程度，除咗影響自己健康，亦都會令到身邊嘅人吸入無色無味，但係依然有林林種種嘅化學物，例如一氧化碳等等嘅物。
其實究竟係煙草商嘅利益緊要啲啊，還是係廣大市民嘅健康緊要啲咧？希望各位議員、政府同埋市民都可以誒支持政府呢項嘅修訂，亦都好似故事中嘅主人翁噉樣堵截源頭，禁止全面禁止另類煙草產。
多謝主席，我係代表香港大學學生會醫學會幹事會嘅。今次嚟支持咧，係誒政府向立法會提交嘅呢個修訂條例草案啦。我哋希望係全面禁止所有嘅電子煙啊、草本煙啊同埋另類煙等等嘅另類煙草產品嘅。咁咧誒，首先咧，坊間流傳咧好多另類吸煙產品咧，有一消息都係話佢哋可以幫煙民去戒。
係一百號位嘅陳尚軍先生。
多謝主席，我係廣大一年級嘅醫科生陳尚君。
心血管和呼吸系統疾病，到不同形式的癌症。
我強烈 urge legislative councillors to pass the amendment bill and ban all alternative smoking products as soon as possible.
In fact, alternative smoking products such as electronic cigarettes are not approved by the FDA as tools of smoke cessation.
oblivious to the health hazards they bring, it's proved that alternative smoking products normalise the act of smoking and should be banned immediately.
not only do these harms affect the smoker himself, but also the non-smoking population through passive exposure to second-hand or third-hand smoking.
各位，我廣大嘅校訓係明德格民，語出《禮禮記大學》，寄予學生認真審視身邊嘅市民，再將知識發揚光大，造福社會。
我同埋今日在座嘅各其他同學學長，憑藉自己學業上面嘅知識，深明另類吸煙產品對社會危害甚重，因而我哋今日喺呢度發言，支持政府今次嘅修訂。
Some argue that alternative smoking products are a means to smoke cessation. However, it must be noted that multiple research has pointed out that these products contain high levels of chemical, such as tobacco and tar, and pose great harm to the body.
而言，我哋更加希望咧，政府係可以更具魄力，對所有嘅煙草產品都係一視同仁，可以研究下全面禁止傳統煙草產品，去展現政府對我哋照顧市民健康嘅承擔，一齊為我哋無煙美好嘅家園去做一個奮鬥。多謝主席。
In view of the variety of trusted and well-researched smoke cessation means currently available, such as nicotine replacement therapy like nicotine patches and gums, which pose relatively much less harm to the body, we have no reason to turn to alternative smoking products for smoke cessation.
All in all, alternative smoking products bring a multitude of health hazards to both smokers and non-smokers. Normalise youngsters' perceptions towards smoking and is not the smoking cessation aid of choice. Therefore, I strongly urge legislative councillors to think for the greater good of the community and pass the amendment bill. Thank you.
戒煙啦，但係其實呢個説法咧係非常之不可取啦，因為好多份咧係在於喺公共衞生醫學嘅期刊研究已經指出過咧，另類煙草產品咧其實係冇噉嘅效用嘅，而且咧呢啲誒呢啲產品咧往往含有重金屬嘅物質啦。雖然佢可能係冇咧無色無味，可能甚至乎係有水果味添，但係其實咧當中咧佢係含有有害。
物質咧係不下於咧係傳統煙嘅，咁咧喺相對於醫療界而家所採用嘅一啲尼古丁取替療療法而言咧，佢係更加危險嘅。所以如果有助戒煙呢個講法咧，實在係天方夜談。咁咧現行嘅法例咧，更加係容許青少年咧輕易噉樣購入電子煙啦。有啲青少年如果唔瞭解電子煙對人體危害嘅話咧，可能
咁咧，所以咧，其實咧，而家使用緊另類吸煙產品嘅年輕人咧，隨之係大幅增加啦。並且係透過呢個門户效應咧，促使社會嘅吸煙人數咧係與日俱增嘅。由此可見咧，其實另類煙草產品唔單止唔可以協助戒煙啦，更加係令到吸煙問題進一步年輕化。可能有人質疑啦，呢個一刀切嘅方法同步今。
咁毋庸置疑啊！呢煙草誒令女煙草產品的確係帶嚟好多種嘅健康問題啦。噉我哋考慮到咧，其實佢發展尚未成熟，我哋希望政府可以防微杜漸，以免波及全港嘅市民，尤其是係我哋年輕一代，我未來嘅社會動力。我哋因此期待條例草案通過之後，香港可以同全球其他三十。
我哋作為香港未來嘅醫學專才，我哋有責任去協助社會認識各類嘅公眾衞生議題，促進公眾健康。咁另類煙草產品其實危害緊我哋每一位市民，所以我哋決意喺呢方面咧係全力支持政府，亦都希望敦促誒全體嘅立法會議員去支持呢個條例草案。長遠。
九十九號位Holy Chan，Thank you, Chairperson. Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen. I'm a year one medical student from the University of Hong Kong. Today, I'm here to express my support for the Smoking Public Health Amendment Bill Two Thousand and Nineteen. In view of all the detrimental effects that alternative smoking products will bring to our society, a
As established by WHO, it is an indisputable fact that all forms of tobacco products bring harm to our society. Alternative smoking products, including electronic cigarettes, heat-not-burn tobacco products and herbal cigarettes, as evidenced by multiple authoritative research, cause a multitude of health hazards, ranging from
currently in our society, alternative smoking products are advertised and marketed under attractive packaging, making them particularly appealing to youngsters who may falsely regard them as less harmful or even harmless products. The fact that more and more teenagers or even children are seen consuming these new tobacco products on
作為一個 harm reduction 策略。
好好運用手上嘅一票，支持二零一九年及現《公共衞生修訂條例草案》，多謝主席。
We have affiliations with the United Nations and the World Health Organization. As a member of our parent federation, the International Federation of Medical Students Associations.
煙草產品嘅良好替代品，佢嘅禍害亦都並非比傳統煙草產品少。研究指出，電子煙使用者有兩倍以上機會成為傳統嘅煙民。
近期新嘅研究甚至指出，電子煙入邊嘅煙草經過反覆嘅熄滅再燃燒，釋出嘅化學產品、化學物質有機會比傳統煙草更加有害。
我由自己身邊同伴嘅經驗可以話畀大家知，事實並非如此。無論切一般嘅數字，或者我自己嘅親身經驗，都話畀我知，另類精組產品理應禁絕。
作為醫學生，我除咗支持今次嘅草案，回應翻啱啱發言人士嘅意見，有啲希望政府更有承擔研究長遠全面禁止傳統煙草產品嘅可能，即係全面禁煙。
Over increasing evidence demonstrates that the use of e-cigarettes serves as a gateway to nicotine dependence. E-cigarette users are three point five times more likely to initiate conventional cigarette smoking than never users.
但請在座各位唔好忘記，我除咗醫學生嘅身份之外，亦都係一位年青人，一位十八歲土生土長嘅香港年青人。作為香港嘅新生代，我同埋身邊嘅同伴一直熱切期待貢獻社會，為香港嘅未來出一分力。
但係，我就眼見香港唔少年輕一輩深受另類吸煙產品嘅禍害，甚至進而終生被煙草產品纏繞。廣大研究發現，百分之八點七嘅中學生曾經吸食電子煙，即係平均每十二個之中就有一個。
一零一號位嘅Matthew Chow。Thank you. My name is Matthew Chow, and I'm a second-year medical student studying at the University of Hong Kong. I'm also the current president of the Asian Medical Students Association Hong Kong, which is the first and largest student-led organisation jointly run by medical students from both HKU and CUHK.
首先，好似啱啱幾位同學提到，世界衞生組織一早已經表明，所有形式嘅煙草使用，包括電子煙、加熱煙、草本煙，都有害。各種另類吸煙產品都會增加患上心血管疾病、呼吸系統疾病同埋癌症嘅風險。大家必須明白，另類吸煙產品並非傳統煙。
香港搞創新咧。
存在於一般公眾。
that the passing of this amendment bill will not only alleviate the adverse effects of
好唔該，跟住係一零三號位嘅周文芳。
香港醫生大麻都食，圍內有黑暗，仲可以判我哋食屎，果然係高級專才。
more importantly, most substance most substance use cases are established during adolescence.
to protect the health of the general public, as well as our future generations. Thank you.
寫封政策研究界叫我哋全禁嘅人，你哋話幫我哋戒煙，其實係拗分定攞資助滋養自己，係一個噉樣樣嘅運作。
There are other viable options such as nicotine replacement therapy patches, that are medically approved and recognised ways during this transition process, and are provided by smoking cessation clinics in Hong Kong.
暴露 to nicotine during adolescence can harm the developing brain and cause addiction and many other adverse health outcomes. Highlighting that now is the time to implement appropriate strategies and policies to combat this.
電子煙包裝新潮，口味獨特。我眼見身邊唔少嘅同學朋友誤以為另類吸煙產品無害，甚至以為佢同傳統煙完全唔同，誤代煙草商嘅廣告陷阱，為另類吸煙產品所害。有聲音指出唔應該全禁，因為只要監管年輕人就唔會再吸食，但係我。
作為醫學生，我有我哋有責任普及醫學知識，畀大眾明白令類吸煙產品嘅危害。作為青年人，我有責任關懷身邊嘅同伴，令佢哋免除受煙草產品困擾終生。而在座各位議員就有責任為香港人把關，守護公眾嘅健康。我希望在座各位。
I'm here today to support the passing of this amendment bill, as we believe that such actions against alternative smoking products are crucial at this point in time. While formulating our stance on this particular issue, we considered the possible benefits of alternative smoking methods as a cessation tool for traditional cigarette users. This logic is otherwise.
However, the WHO also states that eighty percent of e-cigarette users do not quit smoking and instead continue with dual use of both smoking methods. This undoubtedly defeats the purpose of reduction and replacement therapy and may even aggravate health risks associated with nicotine and other chemicals. Moreover.
We also have concerns about the marketing strategies of such products, as novel packaging designs and availability of diverse flavours distract the public from the associated health risks and normalises or even glamorises behaviour that endangers their own health. This is aggravated by misconceptions about the health risks of non-traditional smoking methods.
The Asian Medical Students Association Hong Kong is has been a long time advocate for the human right to health since our inception. We would like to see proactive and precautionary measures undertaken by the government to curb the prevalence and incidence of non traditional smoking methods in the community, rather than a reactionary response to the issue in the future. We believe.
alternative smoking methods on the public, but also increase the public's awareness towards the negative effects of e-cigarettes and tobacco-related products. It is our belief that the government has a responsibility for the health of their peoples, which can be fulfilled only by the provision of adequate health and social measures. And we believe that this amendment is a measure that needs to be.
呢個公聽會有三百人發言咧，噉啊有啲唏噓啦。有醫生或者醫學生話為咗公眾健康要一刀切全禁，但係醫生支持又投票禁止外國叻嘅醫生去香港執業，説好的公眾健康咧，而支持加熱煙合法化嘅醫生，因為怕得罪醫學界嘅大佬，前途盡毀而唔敢出聲。香
嘢。
唔該。
唔produce smoke。
Thank you for the opportunity to express my opinion today.
by the use of hit no burn products.
跟住係呢一節最後一位誒，Mr. Daniel Hardy。
今日所見，原來本地精英都不過如此，食相難看，推我哋落河，自己就扮聖人。
just like my mother, I have several friends here in Hong Kong that they would like to quit cigarettes.
And every year that she comes over here for a nice Hong Kong holiday, she's pushed into going back into smoking cigarettes.
用三分鐘得罪咁多社會言達，身為小市民，其實只係想提出兩點卑微訴求：第一，修訂目前建議版本，容許通過嚴格檢驗嘅加熱煙生產、銷售、使用與進出口；同時加入全面取替傳統香煙時間表。
不如耷低頭揾錢，自然攞到私煙。喂，禁完飛屏同埋加熱煙，就到政府嘅煙草中局啦嘛！我想問最少七十萬傳統煙民係咪準備好搬去大灣區，從而後發食煙咧？如果唔係，咁可唔可以把握最後機會，我哋一齊逆轉無限咧？
第二，行政長官會同行政會議再檢視呢一個影響人數同埋階別眾多嘅民生議題，容許加熱煙合法化，ban全同煙。因為我哋唔係新加坡第二，我哋係香港。最後，香港人壓力真係好大㗎。
Like I've been living in Hong Kong for a few years now, and as such, I bring my mother from overseas on holidays every year for around a month. Nice holiday in Hong Kong. She has been successful at quit to quitting smoking.
或 maybe they don't want to quit, but they want to have the alternative to use hit no burn products that provide better results for quitting than maybe other options. I'm not a smoker, and I would prefer if smoke from cigarettes wasn't around. Hit no burn products.
至於英美日本煙草公司同暴反，睇到佢哋發現其實係冇眼睇。佢有錢，佢有新科技，佢香港請好多人替做經濟效益。佢話支嘢減少危害九成，暴反賣嘢又好有人情味，咁又點啊？香港不嬲出名保守落後，地產掛税雙重標準，幾時輪到呢班人貢獻？
教育界方面，港大學生會刊物學院出咗護理學係講師向學生髮出電郵，只要係公聽會支持全禁新煙，to show support for a total ban on electronic cigarettes，就可以得到學分。呢啲人為咗搶學分而消滅我哋個學霸，就冇人性嘅滅霸Thanos。原本呢一段係想用普通話講嘅，但。
身為另一傳統大學嘅畢業生，除咗關注港大背景嘅Sophia局長有否越權施壓，都有諗Conu係咪專性產教協業會員啊？呢啲即係渣子。佢教育學生本應該更加明白，要循循善誘，不要物極必反。而家個條例嘅版本係示範過猶不及，點解佢要同人一丘之貉咧？
其實你仲係咪泛民咧？定而家反正都分唔清楚，碌過去就算咧。點解你覺得噉樣就一定取悦到最多教育界？Suppose嚟重視理性嘅選民咧，郭醫生或者麻煩你幫我問問阿葉議員。最後我想得罪嘅係權力最大嘅市民，佢哋話公聽會係冇用，我哋只係careless走過。
and。
Hidden brand products.
and not to ban them.
我係Against The Ban。
maybe riding a motorcycle。
I would like today to ask the government to regulate.
banning something only creates illicit trade, and no one wants that.
The possibility to choose between alternatives makes for a free society.
If we ban hit no burn products, what's next? It's
We would like to have the choice of having a drink, having a coffee, having sugar with our coffee.
By regulating hit and burn products, the government can ensure that these products are not sold to minors.
As part of the free society that Hong Kong is, I believe that banning is not the solution.
With regulation and proper education, we can help maintain the low smoking incidents in Hong Kong as well.
但規ulateing the hidden or burn products can help to improve the overall situation for smokers and non-smokers in Hong Kong.
I hope the bills committee members will value the research available in other countries and the opinions expressed today, and they opt for regulating in favour of the people of Hong Kong. Thank you.
We should all have access to an alternative to smoking, especially when research suggests that they have less harmful chemicals, and that even doctors in the UK are recommending them as an alternative to quitting.
你會唔會幫手啊？一齊過去啊！
好唔該曬，大家都聽到鐘聲㗎啦。噉我哋而家休會五分鐘，我哋要個隔離房，唔該曬。